<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://pnpm.io/id/blog</id>
    <title>pnpm Blog</title>
    <updated>2021-12-29T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://pnpm.io/id/blog"/>
    <subtitle>pnpm Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://pnpm.io/id/img/favicon.png</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The year 2021 for pnpm]]></title>
        <id>/2021/12/29/yearly-update</id>
        <link href="https://pnpm.io/id/blog/2021/12/29/yearly-update"/>
        <updated>2021-12-29T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is the end of the year and it was a good year for pnpm, so let's see how it went.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is the end of the year and it was a good year for pnpm, so let&#x27;s see how it went.</p><h2>Usage</h2><h3>Download Stats</h3><p>My goal this year was to beat Bower by the number of downloads. We were able to achieve this goal <a href="https://npm-stat.com/charts.html?package=pnpm&amp;package=bower&amp;from=2021-01-01&amp;to=2021-12-29">in November</a>:</p><p><img src="/img/blog/pnpm-vs-bower-stats.png"/></p><p>pnpm was downloaded about <a href="https://npm-stat.com/charts.html?package=pnpm&amp;from=2016-12-01&amp;to=2021-12-29">3 times more</a> in 2021 than in 2020:</p><p><img src="/img/blog/download-stats-2021.png"/></p><p>:::note</p><p>These stats don&#x27;t even measure all the different ways that pnpm may be installed! They only measure the downloads of the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/pnpm">pnpm npm package</a>. This year we also added compiled binary versions of pnpm, which are shipped differently.</p><p>:::</p><h3>Docs visits</h3><p>We collect some unpersonalized stats from our docs using Google Analytics. In 2021, sometimes we had more than 2,000 unique visitors a week.</p><p><img src="/img/blog/ga-unique-visits-2021.png"/></p><p>Most of our users are from the United States and China.</p><p><img src="/img/blog/countries-2021.png"/></p><h3>GitHub stars</h3><p>Our <a href="https://github.com/pnpm/pnpm">main GitHub repository</a> received +5,000 stars this year.</p><p><img src="/img/blog/stars-2021.png"/></p><h3>New users</h3><p>Our biggest new user this year is <a href="https://github.com/pnpm/pnpm.github.io/pull/89">Bytedance</a> (the company behind TikTok).</p><p>Also, many great open-source projects started to use pnpm. Some switched to pnpm because of its great support of monorepos:</p><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/vuejs/vue-next">Vue</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/vitejs/vite">Vite</a></li><li>and <a href="https://pnpm.io/workspaces#usage-examples">others</a></li></ul><p>Some switched because they like how efficient, fast, and beautiful pnpm is:</p><ul><li><a href="https://twitter.com/Autoprefixer/status/1476226146488692736">Autoprefixer</a></li><li><a href="https://twitter.com/PostCSS/status/1470438664006258701">PostCSS</a></li><li><a href="https://twitter.com/Browserslist/status/1468264308308156419">Browserslist</a></li></ul><h2>Feature Highlights</h2><h3>New lockfile format (since <a href="https://github.com/pnpm/pnpm/releases/tag/v6.0.0">v6.0.0</a>)</h3><p>One of the first and most important changes this year was the new <code>pnpm-lock.yaml</code> format. This was a breaking change, so we had to release v6. But it was a success. The old lockfile was causing Git conflicts frequently. Since the new format was introduced, we did not receive any complaints about Git conflicts.</p><h3>Managing Node.js versions (since <a href="https://github.com/pnpm/pnpm/releases/tag/v6.12.0">v6.12.0</a>)</h3><p>We shipped a new command (<code>pnpm env</code>) that allows to manage Node.js versions. So you may use pnpm instead of Node.js version managers like nvm or Volta.</p><p>Also, pnpm is shipped as a standalone executable, so you can run it even with no Node.js preinstalled on the system.</p><h3>Injecting local dependencies (since <a href="https://github.com/pnpm/pnpm/releases/tag/v6.20.0">v6.20.0</a>)</h3><p>You may &quot;inject&quot; a local dependency. By default, local dependencies are symlinked to <code>node_modules</code> but with this new feature you may instruct pnpm to hard link the files of the package instead.</p><h3>Improved reporting of peer dependency issues (since <a href="https://github.com/pnpm/pnpm/releases/tag/v6.24.0">v6.24.0</a>)</h3><p>Peer dependency issues used to be printed as plain text and it was hard to understand them. They are now all grouped and printed in a nice hierarchy structure.</p><h2>The Competition</h2><h3>Yarn</h3><p>Yarn added a pnpm linker in <a href="https://dev.to/arcanis/yarn-31-corepack-esm-pnpm-optional-packages--3hak#new-install-mode-raw-pnpm-endraw-">v3.1</a>. So Yarn can create a similar node-modules directory structure to the one that pnpm creates.</p><p>Also, the Yarn team plans to implement a content-addressable storage to be more disk space efficient.</p><h3>npm</h3><p>The npm team decided to also adopt the symlinked node-modules directory structure that pnpm uses (related <a href="https://github.com/npm/rfcs/blob/main/accepted/0042-isolated-mode.md">RFC</a>).</p><h3>Others</h3><p><a href="https://twitter.com/jarredsumner/status/1473416431291174912/photo/1">Bun</a> written in Zig and <a href="https://github.com/voltpkg/volt">Volt</a> written in Rust both claim to be faster than npm/Yarn/pnpm. I did not benchmark these new package managers yet.</p><h2>Future Plans</h2><p>Faster, better, best.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Zoltan Kochan</name>
            <uri>http://twitter.com/zoltankochan</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Opsi konfigurasi Node-Modules dengan pnpm]]></title>
        <id>/2020/10/17/node-modules-configuration-options-with-pnpm</id>
        <link href="https://pnpm.io/id/blog/2020/10/17/node-modules-configuration-options-with-pnpm"/>
        <updated>2020-10-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ada banyak cara untuk membuat direktori nodemodules. Your goal must be to create the most strict one but if that is not possible, there are options to make a loose nodemodules as well.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ada banyak cara untuk membuat direktori node_modules. Your goal must be to create the most strict one but if that is not possible, there are options to make a loose node_modules as well.</p><h2>Pengaturan standar</h2><p>Secara standar, pnpm v5 akan membuat node_modules semi-ketat. Semi-ketat berarti aplikasi Anda hanya dapat meminta paket yang ditambahkan sebagai dependensi ke <code>package.json</code> (dengan beberapa pengecualian). Namun, dependensi Anda akan dapat mengakses paket apa pun.</p><p>Konfigurasi standar terlihat seperti ini:</p><pre><code class="language-ini">; All packages are hoisted to node_modules/.pnpm/node_modules
hoist-pattern[]=*

; All types are hoisted to the root in order to make TypeScript happy
public-hoist-pattern[]=*types*

; All ESLint-related packages are hoisted to the root as well
public-hoist-pattern[]=*eslint*
</code></pre><h2>Plug&#x27;n&#x27;Play. The strictest configuration</h2><p>pnpm supports <a href="https://yarnpkg.com/features/pnp">Yarn&#x27;s Plug&#x27;n&#x27;Play</a> since v5.9. With PnP, both your application and the dependencies of your application will have access only to their declared dependencies. This is even stricter then setting <code>hoist=false</code> because inside a monorepo, you&#x27;re application will not be able to access even the dependencies of the root project.</p><p>To use Plug&#x27;n&#x27;Play, set these settings:</p><pre><code class="language-ini">node-linker=pnp
symlink=false
</code></pre><h2>A strict, traditional modules directory</h2><p>If you are not ready to use PnP yet, you can still be strict and only allow packages to access their own dependencies by setting the hoist configuration to false:</p><pre><code class="language-ini">hoist=false
</code></pre><p>However, if some of your dependencies are trying to access packages that they don&#x27;t have in dependencies, you have two options:</p><ol><li><p>Create a <code>pnpmfile.js</code> and use a <a href="/pnpmfile">hook</a> to add the missing dependency to the package&#x27;s manifest.</p></li><li><p>Add a pattern to the <code>hoist-pattern</code> setting. For instance, if the not found module is <code>babel-core</code>, add the following setting to <code>.npmrc</code>:</p><pre><code class="language-ini">hoist-pattern[]=babel-core
</code></pre></li></ol><h2>The worst case - hoisting to the root</h2><p>Some tools might not work even with the default configuration of pnpm, which hoists everything to the root of the virtual store and some packages to the root. In this case, you can hoist either everything or a subset of dependencies to the root of the modules directory.</p><p>Hoisting everything to the the root of node_modules:</p><pre><code class="language-ini">shamefully-hoist=true
</code></pre><p>Hoisting only packages that match a pattern:</p><pre><code class="language-ini">public-hoist-pattern[]=babel-*
</code></pre>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Zoltan Kochan</name>
            <uri>http://twitter.com/zoltankochan</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flat node_modules bukan satu-satunya cara]]></title>
        <id>/2020/05/27/flat-node-modules-is-not-the-only-way</id>
        <link href="https://pnpm.io/id/blog/2020/05/27/flat-node-modules-is-not-the-only-way"/>
        <updated>2020-05-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Pengguna baru pnpm sering bertanya kepada saya tentang struktur aneh node_modules yang dibuat pnpm. Kenapa tidak flat? Di mana semua sub-dependensi?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pengguna baru pnpm sering bertanya kepada saya tentang struktur aneh <code>node_modules</code> yang dibuat pnpm. Kenapa tidak flat? Di mana semua sub-dependensi?</p><blockquote><p>Saya akan berasumsi bahwa pembaca artikel sudah terbiasa dengan flat <code>node_modules</code> dibuat oleh npm dan Yarn. Jika Anda tidak mengerti mengapa npm 3 harus mulai menggunakan flat <code>node_modules</code> di v3, Anda dapat menemukan beberapa prasejarah di <a href="https://www.kochan.io/nodejs/why-should-we-use-pnpm.html">Mengapa kita harus menggunakan pnpm?</a>.</p></blockquote><p>Jadi mengapa <code>node_modules</code> pnpm tidak biasa? Mari buat dua direktori dan jalankan <code>npm add express</code> di salah satunya dan <code>pnpm add express</code> di direktori lainnya. Inilah bagian atas dari apa yang Anda dapatkan di direktori pertama <code>node_modules</code>:</p><pre><code class="language-text">.bin
accepts
array-flatten
body-parser
bytes
content-disposition
cookie-signature
cookie
debug
depd
destroy
ee-first
encodeurl
escape-html
etag
express
</code></pre><p>Anda dapat melihat seluruh direktori <a href="https://github.com/zkochan/comparing-node-modules/tree/master/npm-example/node_modules">disini</a>.</p><p>Dan inilah yang Anda dapatkan di <code>node_modules</code> dibuat oleh pnpm:</p><pre><code class="language-text">.pnpm
.modules.yaml
express
</code></pre><p>Anda dapat memeriksanya <a href="https://github.com/zkochan/comparing-node-modules/tree/master/pnpm5-example/node_modules">disini</a>.</p><p>Jadi di mana semua dependensinya? Hanya ada satu folder di <code>node_modules</code> bernama <code>.pnpm</code> dan symlink bernama <code>express</code>. Nah, kami hanya menginstal <code>express</code>, jadi itu adalah satu-satunya paket yang dapat diakses oleh aplikasi Anda</p><blockquote><p>Baca lebih lanjut tentang mengapa keketatan pnpm adalah hal yang baik <a href="https://medium.com/pnpm/pnpms-strictness-helps-to-avoid-silly-bugs-9a15fb306308">disini</a></p></blockquote><p>Mari kita lihat apa yang ada di dalam <code>express</code>:</p><pre><code class="language-text">▾ node_modules
  ▸ .pnpm
  ▾ express
    ▸ lib
      History.md
      index.js
      LICENSE
      package.json
      Readme.md
    .modules.yaml
</code></pre><p><code>express</code> tidak memiliki <code>node_modules</code>? Di mana semua dependensi <code>express</code>?</p><p>Triknya adalah <code>express</code> hanyalah sebuah symlink. Saat Node.js menyelesaikan dependensi, ia menggunakan lokasi sebenarnya, sehingga tidak mempertahankan symlink. Tapi di mana lokasi sebenarnya dari <code>express</code>, Anda mungkin bertanya?</p><p>Di sini: <a href="https://github.com/zkochan/comparing-node-modules/tree/master/pnpm5-example/node_modules/.pnpm/express@4.17.1/node_modules/express">node_modules/.pnpm/express@4.17.1/node_modules/express</a>.</p><p>Oke, jadi sekarang kita tahu tujuan dari folder <code>.pnpm/</code>. <code>.pnpm/</code> menyimpan semua paket dalam struktur folder datar, sehingga setiap paket dapat ditemukan dalam folder yang dinamai dengan pola ini:</p><pre><code class="language-text">.pnpm/&lt;name&gt;@&lt;version&gt;/node_modules/&lt;name&gt;
</code></pre><p>Kami menyebutnya direktori virtual.</p><p>Struktur datar ini menghindari masalah jalur panjang yang disebabkan oleh <code>node_modules</code> bersarang yang dibuat oleh npm v2 tetapi membuat paket tetap terisolasi tidak seperti <code>node_modules</code> datar yang dibuat oleh npm v3,4,5,6 atau Yarn v1.</p><p>Sekarang mari kita lihat lokasi sebenarnya dari <code>express</code>:</p><pre><code class="language-text">  ▾ express
    ▸ lib
      History.md
      index.js
      LICENSE
      package.json
      Readme.md
</code></pre><p>Apakah itu penipuan? Masih kekurangan <code>node_modules</code>! Trik kedua dari struktur <code>node_modules</code> pnpm adalah bahwa dependensi paket berada pada tingkat direktori yang sama dengan lokasi sebenarnya dari paket dependen. Jadi dependensi <code>express</code> tidak ada di <code>.pnpm/express@4.17.1/node_modules/express/node_modules/</code> tetapi dalam <a href="https://github.com/zkochan/comparing-node-modules/tree/master/pnpm5-example/node_modules/.pnpm/express@4.17.1/node_modules">.pnpm/express@4.17.1/node_modules/</a>:</p><pre><code class="language-text">▾ node_modules
  ▾ .pnpm
    ▸ accepts@1.3.5
    ▸ array-flatten@1.1.1
    ...
    ▾ express@4.16.3
      ▾ node_modules
        ▸ accepts
        ▸ array-flatten
        ▸ body-parser
        ▸ content-disposition
        ...
        ▸ etag
        ▾ express
          ▸ lib
            History.md
            index.js
            LICENSE
            package.json
            Readme.md
</code></pre><p>Semua dependensi <code>express</code> adalah symlink ke direktori yang sesuai di <code>node_modules/.pnpm/</code>. Menempatkan dependensi <code>express</code> satu tingkat ke atas memungkinkan menghindari symlink melingkar.</p><p>Jadi seperti yang Anda lihat, meskipun struktur <code>node_modules</code> pnpm tampak tidak biasa pada awalnya:</p><ol><li>itu sepenuhnya kompatibel dengan Node.js</li><li>paket dikelompokkan dengan baik dengan dependensinya</li></ol><p>Strukturnya sedikit <a href="/how-peers-are-resolved">lebih kompleks</a> untuk paket dengan dependensi rekan tetapi idenya sama: menggunakan symlink untuk membuat sarang dengan struktur direktori datar.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Zoltan Kochan</name>
            <uri>http://twitter.com/zoltankochan</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>